According to rumors on the Net,
ネット:network
（ヤサコ）ネットのウワサによると
a few years ago, an Encoder tried to devastate the Space.
数[しばしば]:often/again and again/frequently, 数[かず]:number/amount, 暗号[あんごう]:code/password/cipher, 屋[や]:(something) shop|somebody who sells (something) or works as (something)|somebody with a (certain) personality trait||, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 破壊[はかい]:destruction/disruption|(application) crash
数年前に ある暗号屋が
空間を破壊しようとしたそうです
暗号[あんごう]:code/password/cipher, 屋[や]:(something) shop|somebody who sells (something) or works as (something)|somebody with a (certain) personality trait||
でも その暗号屋がどうなったのか
誰も知りません
But nobody knows what happened to this Encoder.
新しい[あたらしい]:new/novel/fresh, 友達[ともだち]:friend/companion
（マイコ）
もう１人の新しいお友達は…
Our second new friend is...
天沢(あまさわ)さん 天沢勇子(ゆうこ)さん
Amasawa.
Yuko Amasawa.
偶然[ぐうぜん]:coincidence|by chance|contingency (philosophy), 同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway
あら 偶然
２人とも同じユウコなのね
Oh, what a coincidence.
You two have the same name. Yuko.
よろしく:well/properly|best regards
（イサコ）天沢勇子です よろしく
I'm Yuko Amasawa.
Pleased to meet you.
（フミエ）
金沢(かなざわ)ってことは―
Kanazawa...?
So her parents probably work for a glasses company.
Daikoku City
The Hacker's Club
親[おや]:parent|dealer (in cards, mahjong, etc.)|founder|, 親[しん]:intimacy|close relative|pro- (e.g. pro-American, pro-Japanese, etc.), メガネ:spectacles/glasses, 会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace, かしら:I wonder, かしら:head|hair (on one's head)
あいつの親も
メガネ会社の人かしらね
I don't know...
（ヤサコ）さあ？
でも 金沢には―
But there wasn't any Encoder in Kanazawa.
暗号[あんごう]:code/password/cipher, 屋[や]:(something) shop|somebody who sells (something) or works as (something)|somebody with a (certain) personality trait||, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
暗号屋なんて
いなかったわよ
暗号[あんごう]:code/password/cipher, 屋[や]:(something) shop|somebody who sells (something) or works as (something)|somebody with a (certain) personality trait||, いろんな:various, 都市[とし]:town/city/municipal, 伝説[でんせつ]:tradition/legend/folklore
（フミエ）暗号屋には
いろんな都市伝説があって
There are a lot of urban legends about Encoders,
正体[しょうたい]:true character/true form|consciousness, 目的[もくてき]:purpose/goal/aim
正体や目的が
よく分からないのよ
but their true nature and objectives are unknown.
I thought their objective was to collect metabugs.
集める[あつめる]:to collect/to assemble/to gather, 目的[もくてき]:purpose/goal/aim
メタバグを集めるのが
目的じゃない？
（フミエ）それがウワサでは
Rumors say that what they take from the Space isn't just metabugs.
空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 取り出す[とりだす]:to take out/to produce|to fetch
空間から取り出すのは
メタバグだけじゃないの
取り出す[とりだす]:to take out/to produce|to fetch
（ヤサコ）何を取り出すの？
So what else do they take?
Hmm, let's see...
例えば[たとえば]:for example/for instance/e.g.
さあ… そうねえ
例えばミチコさんよ
For example, Miss Michiko.
ミ… ミチコさん？
Miss Michiko?
そうよ
Yeah.
呼び出す[よびだす]:to summon/to call (e.g. phone)|to invoke (e.g. subroutine), 契約[けいやく]:contract/compact/agreement
でね ミチコさんを
呼び出して契約すると
I heard that if you call out Miss Michiko and make a contract with her,
願い事[ねがいごと]:wish/dream/prayer, かなえる:to grant (request, wish)/to answer (prayer)|to fulfill (conditions)
なんでも願い事を
かなえてくれるんだってさ
she'll make whatever you wish for come true!
Like having better grades in school,
テスト:test, 成績[せいせき]:results/record/grades, 上がる[あがる]:to rise|to enter (esp. from outdoors)|to enter (a school)||, 家[いえ]:house|family|lineage, 家[うち, ち]:house/home (one's own)|(one's) family, 急[きゅう]:urgent|sharp|rapid||, 金持ち[かねもち]:rich person
テストの成績が上がるとか
家が急にお金持ちになるとか
or making your family become rich, overnight!
探りを入れる[さぐりをいれる]:to probe/to search/to sound out
ちょっと探りを入れてみようか
Let's start our investigation.
こんにちは:hello/good day (daytime greeting), 昨日[きのう, さくじつ]:yesterday, いろいろ:various|various colors (colours)
こんにちは
昨日はいろいろあったわね
Hello.
So many things happened yesterday.
よろしく:well/properly|best regards
私はフミエ よろしくね
My name is Fumie.
Nice to meet you.
よろしく:well/properly|best regards
よろしく
Nice to meet you too.
こっちは優子(ゆうこ)よ
And this here is Yuko.
あら あなたも
ユウコっていうのね
So your name is Yuko too, right?
偶然[ぐうぜん]:coincidence|by chance|contingency (philosophy)
偶然ね
What a coincidence!
ニックネーム:nickname, 優しい[やさしい]:tender/kind/gentle, 書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw
小此木(おこのぎ)さんのニックネームは
優しいと書いてヤサコ
Okonogi's nickname is Yasako, since her name is written with the kanji for "yasashii".
勇ましい[いさましい]:brave/valiant|stirring, 書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw
あなたは
勇ましいって書くのよね
And yours is written with the kanji for "isamashii", right?
Isamashii means brave and courageous
としたら イサコだわ
So your nickname should be Isako!
よっ イサコ！
Cool, Isako!
ちょうど:exactly/precisely|as if, ちょうど:supplies/furniture/fixtures, 語呂[ごろ]:sound (of a sentence)/euphony, 合う[あう, おう]:to come together|to fit|to be profitable|
ちょうど語呂も合ってて
いいじゃない
Your names make a pun! Cool!
ヤサコ イサコって
Yasako and Isako!
Stop it, we're not a comedy duo!
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit, 漫才師[まんざいし]:(one of) a comic duo
（ヤサコ）や… やめてよ
漫才師じゃあるまいし
Amasawa,
仲良く[なかよく]:on good terms with/on cordial terms with|to make friends with
天沢さん
これから仲良くしましょう
let's be good friends.
So please, don't do things like yesterday anymore.
昨日[きのう, さくじつ]:yesterday, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
でも 昨日みたいなことは
もうしないでね
Yesterday?
昨日[きのう, さくじつ]:yesterday
昨日？
今回[こんかい]:now/this time/lately, 初めて[はじめて]:for the first time|only after ... is it .../only when ... do you ...
あなたたちに会うのは
今回が初めてよ
Today's the first time I met either of you.
Now would you please stop talking to me?
悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing, あんまり:remainder/rest|not very (with negative sentence), 話しかける[はなしかける]:to address (someone)/to accost a person|to begin to talk
悪いけど
あんまり話しかけないでくれる？
ふーん:hmm/well ...|roughly
ふーん
I don't know who Your Majesty is,
様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state
あんたが
何様なのか知らないけれど
but don't you ever lay your hands on other people's pets again!
二[に, ふた]:two, 二[アル]:two, 度[たび, たんび]:time (three times, each time, etc.)/times, 度[ど]:degree (angle, temperature, scale, etc.)|counter for occurrences and times|strength (of alcohol), 様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state, ペット:pet, ペット:polyethylene terephthalate/PET, 手を出す[てをだす]:to turn one's hand to|to get involved in|to start a fight
二度と人様のペットに
手を出すんじゃないわよ
Got it?
分かった？
What if I say I don't?
分からないと言ったら？
Then I'll make you understand; even if I need to use all my power.
実力[じつりょく]:(real) ability/true strength|arms
実力で分からせるまでよ
Hey, Busue!
"Busue" is a word game composed
of the words Busu (ugly) and Fumie.
（ダイチ）おい ブスエ！
Are you recruiting again?
勧誘[かんゆう]:invitation/solicitation/canvassing, 探偵[たんてい]:detective/sleuth/investigator, クラブ:nightclub, クラブ:club/fraternity/sorority
お前 また勧誘してんのか？
探偵ごっこクラブに
For your "let's play the detective" club?
You're such a pest.
うっさいわね
Nobody is gonna join your loser club!
お前のヘボクラブになんか
誰も入んねえよ
Anyway, how about joining my club?
クラブ:nightclub, クラブ:club/fraternity/sorority, 入れる[いれる]:to put in|to admit|to accept||
それより俺のクラブに入れよ
It's a real cool club!
すんごい:terrible/dreadful/terrific, クール:cool (temperature, color, etc.), クラブ:nightclub, クラブ:club/fraternity/sorority
すんげえクールなクラブなんだぜ
フン
シカト:ostracism/ignoring someone/leaving someone out
ああ… なんだ　シカトか？
Hey, are you ignoring me?
How dare you ignore the Great Daichi!
様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state, シカト:ostracism/ignoring someone/leaving someone out
この俺様をシカトするのか？
No way she would ever join a loser boys-only club like yours!
ばかり:only/merely|approximately, 決まる[きまる]:to be decided/to be settled|to look good in (clothes)
そんな男ばかりのダメクラブ
ダメに決まってるじゃない
Shrimpy!
チビスケ
What?! Who ya callin' a shrimp?!
呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||
んだと チビスケ！
ミチコさん呼ぶぞ！
I'm gonna call out Michiko!
呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||
私だって ミチコさん呼ぶわよ
I'm gonna call out Michiko too!
Shut up!
うるさい:noisy/loud|annoying
（イサコ）うるさい！
Both of you runts are never to speak to me again.
どっち:which way/which direction|which one (esp. of two alternatives), 話しかける[はなしかける]:to address (someone)/to accost a person|to begin to talk
どっちのチビスケも
もう話しかけるな
Hey boss.
やっぱり:too/also|still, 転校生[てんこうせい]:transfer student/student changing schools
（ナメッチ）オヤビン
やっぱりやっちゃるですか 転校生
It looks like that transfer student really wants a lesson.
Of course she does.
当たり前[あたりまえ]:natural/reasonable|usual
当たり前だ
But boss,
転校生[てんこうせい]:transfer student/student changing schools, だまくらかす:to trick/to cheat/to deceive
でも オヤビン
うぶな転校生をだまくらかして
weren't you the one bent on tricking her
and having her join as the first female member in the club?
我が[わが]:my/our/one's own, クラブ:nightclub, クラブ:club/fraternity/sorority, 初[はつ, うい]:first/new, 初[うぶ]:innocent/naive|birth-, 女子[じょし, おなご]:woman/girl, 女子[めこ, メコ]:vagina|girl, 構成員[こうせいいん]:members/member/constituent, 仕立てる[したてる]:to tailor|to train|to make it seem like||
我がクラブ初の女子構成員に
仕立てるぞって
意気[いき]:spirit/heart/disposition, 込む[こむ]:to be crowded|to be complex|to go into||
意気込んでたじゃないっすか
She dared to ignore me.
無視[むし]:disregarding/ignoring, やがる:verb suffix indicating hatred and contempt, or disdain for another's action, あんな:such (about something or someone distant from both speaker and listener, or about a situation unfamiliar to both speaker and listener)/so/that, あんな:Anna or Anwa era (968.8.13-970.3.25), クラブ:nightclub, クラブ:club/fraternity/sorority, 入れる[いれる]:to put in|to admit|to accept||
俺を無視しやがった
あんなヤツはクラブに入れてやらん
I'll never let her join my club.
Then what about that other transfer student?
あっち:that way (direction distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|that one (something physically distant from both speaker and listener, or something not visible but known by both speaker and listener), 転校生[てんこうせい]:transfer student/student changing schools
じゃあ あっちの転校生は
どうなんすか？
She's already Busue's friend.
すでに:already/too late
（ダイチ）
あいつは すでにブスエの仲間だ
So she's our enemy.
我々[われわれ]:we, 敵[かたき]:rival|revenge|spouse, 敵[てき]:opponent/rival|menace
我々の敵だ
We have to teach both of them a good lesson from the start!
最初[さいしょ]:beginning/outset/first
最初にガツーンと
やっとかなくてはならん
Wh-What's going on?!
な… 何これ？
消える[きえる]:to go out/to vanish/to disappear
あっ 消えない
It won't go away!
This prank...
イタズラ:mischief/prank/trick
このイタズラは…
（２人）ニィ～
Say, "Share root access".
管理[かんり]:control/management (e.g. of a business), 共有[きょうゆう]:joint ownership/co-ownership/sharing
ヤサコ “管理共有”って言って
Sh-Share root access!
管理[かんり]:control/management (e.g. of a business), 共有[きょうゆう]:joint ownership/co-ownership/sharing
か… 管理共有
フーン
ふーん:hmm/well ...|roughly
ふーん…
Okay then.
問題[もんだい]:question (e.g. on a test)|problem (e.g. societal, political)|question (i.e. doubt)||, もらえる:to be able to receive/to be able to take|could you (give me)
じゃあ この問題
天沢さん やってもらえる？
Amasawa, could you solve this problem?
んっ？　ニィ～
Now let's see what she's capable of.
手並み[てなみ]:skill, 拝見[はいけん]:seeing/look at
お手並み拝見といきましょうか
消える[きえる]:to go out/to vanish/to disappear
消えてく？　くっ…
It's disappearing?
It looks like they both have the same speed.
スピード:speed, 互角[ごかく]:equality/evenness/par
スピードは互角のようね
But she's writing the answer at the same time.
答え[こたえ, いらえ]:answer/reply/response, 書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw, ながら:while/during|while
でも答えを書きながらよ
Huh?
操作[そうさ]:operation/management|manipulating to one's benefit, かしら:I wonder, かしら:head|hair (on one's head)
あら？　どこで操作してるのかしら
Where is she operating from?
How can she operate...?
操作[そうさ]:operation/management|manipulating to one's benefit
どうやって操作してるんだ？
Who knows?
（ナメッチ）さあ？
（ダイチ）クソ！
Crap!
んっ？　それは なんすか？
What's that?
Critical Error
はい 天沢さん よくできました
Good job, Amasawa.
倍[ばい]:twice/double|times, 返す[かえす]:to return (something)|to turn over|to pay back|
３倍返しっすね オヤビン
I'll pay her back double for that!
許す[ゆるす]:to permit|to exempt (from fine)|to confide in|, メガネ:spectacles/glasses, やがる:verb suffix indicating hatred and contempt, or disdain for another's action
（ダイチ）許せん！
俺のメガネをこんなにしやがって…
I'll never forgive her
Downloading the Auto-Restore
for doing this to my glasses!
全然[ぜんぜん]:not at all (with neg. verb)|wholly/entirely, 動かす[うごかす]:to move|to inspire|to change||
それにしても あいつ
全然 手を動かさなかったっすね
What's amazing
is that she didn't even move her hand.
そうなんだよ
Exactly!
手作業[てさぎょう]:manual labor/manual labour/manual procedures, 閉じる[とじる]:to close (e.g. book, eyes, meeting, etc.)/to shut, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing, バナー:banner, 厳選[げんせん]:careful selection/careful screening/hand-picking
手作業でしか閉じられない
タチの悪いバナーを厳選したのに
I chose especially nasty banners that could only be closed with hand movements, but...
もしかし:perhaps/maybe/by some chance, イマーゴ:imago, 隠す[かくす]:to hide/to conceal, 機能[きのう]:function/facility/faculty, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
（ガチャギリ）
もしかしたら イマーゴって
隠し機能かもしれねえぞ
It could be the so-called "Imago" secret function.
イマーゴ:imago
イマーゴ？
Imago?
メガネ:spectacles/glasses, 公開[こうかい]:opening to the public/making available to the public/putting on display, 機能[きのう]:function/facility/faculty
（ガチャギリ）メガネには
公開されてない機能があってな
You know glasses have hidden functions that are unknown to the public, right?
Yes.
イマーゴ:imago
それがイマーゴだ
That's what Imago is.
ええ 分かったわ
（ナメッチ）へえー
Yes.
Understood.
（ダイチ）
そんなの聞いたことねえぞ
Never heard of it.
不具合[ふぐあい]:flaw/defect|inconvenient, 使用[しよう]:use/application/employment, 禁止[きんし]:prohibition/inhibition/ban, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
（ガチャギリ）
ああ なんだか不具合が出てな
使用禁止になったらしい
Some kind of bug came out with them.
So its use has been forbidden.
メーカー:manufacturer/maker, ひた隠し[ひたかくし]:cover-up/hiding at all costs
それをメーカーが
ひた隠しにしてるってウワサだ
Rumors suggest that the manufacturer is hiding it like hell.
一体[いったい]:...the heck (e.g. "what the heck?")|one object|one form||, どんな:what/what kind of|(with -temo, demo, etc.) any(body, thing, means, etc.), 機能[きのう]:function/facility/faculty
（ダイチ）で 一体 どんな機能だ？
So what function is that?
Well,
頭[とう]:counter for large animals (e.g. head of cattle), 頭[あたま, かしら]:head|hair (on one's head)|mind||, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||, メガネ:spectacles/glasses, 操作[そうさ]:operation/management|manipulating to one's benefit, 機能[きのう]:function/facility/faculty, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
それがね 頭で考えただけで
メガネを操作できる機能らしいのよ
they say that it allows you to control your glasses with your mind.
へえー そんなことできるんだ
I didn't know that was possible.
機能[きのう]:function/facility/faculty, アクセス:access, 方法[ほうほう]:method/process/manner
あの子 その機能に
アクセスできる方法を
I guess that girl somehow discovered how to access that function—
手に入れる[てにいれる]:to obtain/to procure
どこかで手に入れたのかも
（２人）ニィ～
原始的[げんしてき]:primitive/original, イタズラ:mischief/prank/trick, 対抗[たいこう]:opposition/antagonism
でも原始的なイタズラには
対抗できないわね
But there's nothing she can do about real-life pranks.
あ～あ
しっかり:tightly (holding on)/firmly|strongly (built), 受け取る[うけとる]:to receive/to get|to take, 転校生[てんこうせい]:transfer student/student changing schools
しっかり受け取れよ 転校生
Be careful when you take stuff, transfer student.
あら どうしたの？
What happened?
こぼす:to spill/to drop|to grumble
こいつが こぼしたんです
She made it all fall out.
（マイコ）そうなの？　天沢さん
Is that true, Amasawa?
ホント:truth/reality/actuality, からい:spicy/hot|salty, からい:salty (taste)/briny
（アイコ）ホント
せちがらいヤツよね ダイチって
Daichi sure is a pest.
どっち:which way/which direction|which one (esp. of two alternatives), 気味[きみ, きび]:sensation/feeling|tendency, 気味[ぎみ]:-like/-looking/-looked
どっちもいい気味よ
Serves them right.
どういう:somehow/how/in what way
（ヤサコ）あのダイチ君って
どういう子なの？
Just what kind of person is Daichi?
単なる[たんなる]:mere/simple/sheer, イタズラ:mischief/prank/trick, 坊主[ぼうず]:Buddhist priest|close-cropped hair|boy|, メガネ:spectacles/glasses
単なるイタズラ坊主よ
メガネさえなけりゃね
He's just a little rascal...
...without his glasses.
最近[さいきん]:most recent/these days/right now, 始める[はじめる]:to start|to open (e.g. a store)|to start ...
でも 最近
こんなこと始めたのよ
But lately,
he's started doing things like this.
きゃく:guest/visitor|customer, きゃく:counter for chairs or seats
くろきゃく？
Black Customers?
読む[よむ]:to read|to count|to guess, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
“ヘイクー”って読むらしいわ
It's read "Hackers".
中国語[ちゅうごくご]:Chinese (language), ハッカー:hacker, 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance
中国語で
“ハッカー”って意味なんだって
I heard this way of writing comes from Chinese.
道具[どうぐ]:tool/implement|means, 通販[つうはん]:mail order/online shopping/e-commerce, 駄菓子[だがし]:cheap sweets, 屋[や]:(something) shop|somebody who sells (something) or works as (something)|somebody with a (certain) personality trait||, 買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
使う道具は どっかの
通販駄菓子屋で買ってるらしいわ
Some say that they use special items bought at online dagashi stores.
（ダイチ）ヘコんでる ヘコんでる
She sure gave up easily!
おとなしい:obedient/docile/quiet
これで おとなしくなりますかね？
With this, she's gonna be real quiet.
放課後[ほうかご]:after school
いや 放課後もやるぞ
No, we're gonna do it again after school.
例えば[たとえば]:for example/for instance/e.g.
例えば ミチコさんよ
For example, Miss Michiko.
ミチコさんか…
Miss Michiko?
あの… イサコちゃん
Um,
Isako...
天沢さん
Amasawa...
用[よう]:business|use|for the use of ...|, 手短[てみじか]:short/brief
用があるなら手短に言って
If you've got something to say, make it fast.
昨日[きのう, さくじつ]:yesterday, 驚く[おどろく]:to be surprised/to be astonished
あっ あの…
なんか昨日は驚いたけど
Well,
although I was a bit scared yesterday,
仲良く[なかよく]:on good terms with/on cordial terms with|to make friends with
私 あなたと
仲良くしたいと思ってるの
I really want to be your friend.
同時[どうじ]:simultaneous/concurrent/same time, 引っ越す[ひっこす, ひきこす]:to move (house)/to change residence, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 偶然[ぐうぜん]:coincidence|by chance|contingency (philosophy), 思える[おもえる]:to seem/to appear likely
同時に引っ越してくるなんて
偶然とは思えないし
I can't believe it's just a coincidence that we both moved here at the same time.
友達[ともだち]:friend/companion
お友達になりましょ
So let's be friends.
みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
私は あんたたちみたいに
I don't like people
気安い[きやすい]:relaxed/familiar/easy to access, 群れる[むれる]:to crowd/to flock/to swarm, 生き物[いきもの]:living thing/animal, 好き[すき]:liking/fondness/love, 好き[ずき]:-phil/-phile|being attractive (to)
気安く群れる生き物が
好きじゃないの
who blindly flock to others like you do.
From Maiko-sensei to Miss Amazawa - I have something to tell you, come here immediately.
（ヤサコ）私だって…
I don't...
気安い[きやすい]:relaxed/familiar/easy to access, 群れる[むれる]:to crowd/to flock/to swarm, なんか:things like .../or something like that ... (often derogatory), なんか:something
私だって
気安く群れてなんかいないわ
I don't blindly flock to others.
嫌う[きらう]:to hate/to dislike/to loathe, 怖い[こわい]:scary/frightening|(I'm) afraid
誰だって嫌われるのは怖いわ
Everyone's afraid to be left alone.
他[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 他[た]:other (esp. people and abstract matters), 当たる[あたる]:to be hit|to touch|to be equivalent to||
でも それで他の人に
キツく当たっても
But being unpleasant with people
友達[ともだち]:friend/companion
友達はできないわ
won't help you make any friends.
Me?
私が？
当たる[あたる]:to be hit|to touch|to be equivalent to||, たがる:wanting to .../eager to .../curious to ..., 男子[だんし]:youth/young man
キツく当たりたがってるのは
あの男子でしょ
The one being unpleasant
is that boy, isn't it?
でも…
But...
当てる[あてる]:to hit|to expose|to apply (e.g. patch)||, あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair)
当ててあげようか
Let me guess.
学校[がっこう]:school
あなた 前の学校で
I'm guessing
you caused some trouble in your last school.
トラブル:trouble, 起こす[おこす]:to raise|to wake|to cause||
何かトラブルを
起こしたんじゃない？
いじめ:bullying/teasing
いじめ？
A bully?
Wh—
何言ってるの？
What are you talking about?
図星[ずぼし]:bull's-eye/mark
（イサコ）図星のようね
So I was right.
いじめる:to tease/to torment/to persecute
いじめてたか
いじめられてたか
Were you the bully or the bullied?
バレる:to leak out (a secret)/to be exposed (a lie, improper behaviour, etc.) (behavior), 演技[えんぎ]:acting/performance
それがバレないように
演技してたんでしょ？
You were acting so that no one would ever figure it out, right?
街[がい]:.. street/.. quarter/.. district, 街[まち, ちょう]:town|street|109.09 m||, 心機一転[しんきいってん]:changing one's attitude/turning over a new leaf/getting a fresh start, うまい:skillful/skilful|delicious, デビュー:debut
この街では心機一転
うまいことデビューしようって？
And you were thinking that you would start a new life here.
他[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 他[た]:other (esp. people and abstract matters), だませる:to trick/to cheat|to coax, ごまかせる:to deceive/to falsify|to dodge
他はだませても
私の目はごまかせないわ
You may fool others,
but you can't fool me.
秘密[ひみつ]:secret|secret|esoteric teachings
大丈夫　あなたの秘密は
誰にも言わないわ
Don't worry.
I won't tell anyone about your secret.
（フミエ）あっ ヤサコ
Yasako.
情報[じょうほう]:information/news|information, 手に入れる[てにいれる]:to obtain/to procure
ある情報を手に入れたわ
I happened to hear a certain bit of information.
面白い[おもしろい]:interesting|amusing|pleasant, ことになる:it has been decided (so) that/it has been arranged (so) that|it is the result (of)
面白いことになりそうよ
Something tells me things are gonna get interesting.
面白い[おもしろい]:interesting|amusing|pleasant
（ヤサコ）面白いこと？
Interesting?
戦争[せんそう]:war
戦争よ
A war!
パケット:packet, 料金[りょうきん]:fee/charge/fare, いくら:how much?/how many?|even
（ガチャギリ）
パケット料金は いくらになった？
How much did you pay for that?
お年玉[おとしだま]:New Year's gift (usu. money given to a child by relatives and visitors), 換算[かんさん, かんざん]:conversion (e.g. yen to dollars)/change/exchange
（ナメッチ）あちゃ～
お年玉換算で２年分っすね
Ouch!
It was the equivalent of two years' otoshidama.
おのれ:oneself (itself, etc.)|I/me
おのれ～！
Dammit!
今度[こんど]:this time|next time|recently, メガネ:spectacles/glasses, 倍[ばい]:twice/double|times, 返し[かえし]:reversal|return gift|barb (on a fishing hook)|, してやる:to do for (someone)
今度はメガネで
３倍返しにしてやるのだ！
This time, with these glasses, I'll make her pay two—no, three times!
（ダイチ）おい ４年！
（アキラ）あっ はい
Hey, fourth year!
Yessir!
メッセージ:message, 送る[おくる]:to send (a thing)|to take or escort (a person somewhere)|to bid farewell (to the departed)||
メッセージは送ったか？
（アキラ）あっ はい
Did you send the message?
Y-Yes!
ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly, サーバー:server, 職員室[しょくいんしつ]:staff room, 偽装[ぎそう]:camouflage/disguise|pretense
ちゃんとサーバーも
職員室に偽装して―
I just sent it by using the server in the school's office as a proxy.
さっき:some time ago/just now, さっき:thirst for blood/bloodlust/determination to kill, 送る[おくる]:to send (a thing)|to take or escort (a person somewhere)|to bid farewell (to the departed)||
さっき送りました
先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy
先生 どこですか…
Teacher, where are—?
ハァ…
ミサイル:missile, 安物[やすもの]:cheap article/poor quality article
ミサイルは安物のようね
A cheap missile weapon, huh?
さっき:some time ago/just now, さっき:thirst for blood/bloodlust/determination to kill
さっきのガキどもか
Is it those pests from before?
この！　この！
Dammit! Dammit!
直進[ちょくしん]:going right on/going straight ahead
（アキラ）直進くんです
Here's a Mister Forthright!
Hey, fourth year,
どんどん:drumming (noise)|rapidly/steadily, 補給[ほきゅう]:supply/supplying/replenishment
（ダイチ）
おい ４年 どんどん補給しろ
go recharge some more!
あっ はい
Yes, sir!
“はい”じゃねえ　“へい”だ
Don't say, "Yes, sir!"
Say, "Yeah!"
へ… へい
Yeah!
直進[ちょくしん]:going right on/going straight ahead, 破れる[われる]:to break|to split|to be divided|, 破れる[やぶれる]:to get torn/to tear|to be broken off (of negotiations, etc.)
クソ！　直進くんじゃ破れねえ
Damn!
The Mister Forthright won't be able beat her!
安物[やすもの]:cheap article/poor quality article
安物っすからねえ
It's a cheap weapon after all...
追跡[ついせき]:chase/pursuit|following up
追跡くんを出せ
Take out the Mister Chase!
へい
Yeah!
当たる[あたる]:to be hit|to touch|to be equivalent to||
当たったか？
Did it get her?
（ガチャギリ）分からねえ
Dunno.
発[はつ]:departure|sending|engine||, いくら:how much?/how many?|even
１発 いくらだ？
How much is a shot?
発[はつ]:departure|sending|engine||
（ナメッチ）１発 200メタっす
200 meta per shot.
値切る[ねぎる]:to drive a bargain/to beat down the price/to haggle
値切ってか？
And with the discount?
値切る[ねぎる]:to drive a bargain/to beat down the price/to haggle
（ナメッチ）値切ってっす
Discount included.
からい:spicy/hot|salty, からい:salty (taste)/briny
あ～ せちがらいぜ
Ah, what a cruel world...!
追跡[ついせき]:chase/pursuit|following up, 袋[ふくろ]:bag|skin of an orange (and other like fruits)|dead end|, 袋[たい]:counter for things inside a bag, 使い切る[つかいきる]:to use up/to exhaust/to wear out
（アキラ）
追跡くん １袋 使い切りました
I used up one bag of Mister Chase.
最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments, 袋[ふくろ]:bag|skin of an orange (and other like fruits)|dead end|, 袋[たい]:counter for things inside a bag
最後の袋も出しますか？
Should I take out the last bag?
いや それは待て
No, wait.
鉄壁[てっぺき]:iron wall/impregnable fortress, ハッキング:hacking, 方法[ほうほう]:method/process/manner
おい まだか？
鉄壁のハッキング方法
Haven't you found a way to hack that steel wall yet?
近い[ちかい]:near|close (in time)|close (relationship)||, 方法[ほうほう]:method/process/manner, 載る[のる]:to be placed on/to be set on|to appear (in print)
近い方法は載ってるんだが…
I found a way for hacking it, but...
応用[おうよう]:application/put to practical use|applied
これ… これを応用すれば
いいんじゃないですか？
You just have to apply this.
んっ？　あっ そうか！
Oh, yeah!
いねえな
She's not here.
連絡[れんらく]:to contact|contacting|connection|, 通路[つうろ]:passage/pathway/roadway, テリトリー:territory
連絡通路から こっちは
俺たちのテリトリーなんだ
From the access route on, it's our territory.
逃がす[にがす]:to set free/to let go|to miss (e.g. a chance)
逃がさんぞ
I won't let her get away.
（イサコ）いつもこれだ
It's always like this.
あっち:that way (direction distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|that one (something physically distant from both speaker and listener, or something not visible but known by both speaker and listener), 手を出す[てをだす]:to turn one's hand to|to get involved in|to start a fight
何もしてなくても
あっちから手を出してくる
Even if I do nothing,
others will still attack me.
面白い[おもしろい]:interesting|amusing|pleasant
（フミエ）こりゃあ面白いわ
This is really getting interesting.
気づく[きづく]:to notice/to recognize/to recognise
気づかれるなよ
Don't get caught.
こりゃ:hey there/I say/see here
な… なんだ こりゃ？
Wh-What's this?
A malignant access has been denied.
防壁[ぼうへき]:protective wall/bulwark, 阻止[そし]:obstruction/check/hindrance
（ガチャギリ）防壁が阻止したぞ
Her defensive wall has intercepted the attack!
最近[さいきん]:most recent/these days/right now, あちこち:here and there/all around|to get things in the wrong order (back to front), 道路[どうろ]:road/highway, 書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw
（アキラ）今のは 最近
あちこちの道路に書いてあるやつだ
That's the same sign I've seen 'round here lately!
防壁[ぼうへき]:protective wall/bulwark, 通る[とおる]:to go by|to run (between)|to go indoors||, 問題[もんだい]:question (e.g. on a test)|problem (e.g. societal, political)|question (i.e. doubt)||
（ダイチ）
防壁を通らなきゃ問題ねえや
It doesn't matter as long as the wall isn't breached!
隠れる[かくれる]:to hide/to be hidden/to conceal oneself
それで隠れたつもりかよ
So she thinks she's out of our sight, huh?
やれ！
Attack!
直進[ちょくしん]:going right on/going straight ahead, 撃ち込む[うちこむ]:to fire into (e.g. a crowd)/to launch (e.g. missiles)/to lob (e.g. grenades)
直進くんを撃ち込め！
Fire the Mister Forthright!
相手[あいて]:companion|other party|opponent (sports, etc.), してやる:to do for (someone)
相手してやるわ
Fine, I'll play with you.
先[さき]:previous|point (e.g. pencil)|head (of a line)||, 先[せん]:former/previous|first move (in go, shogi, etc.), 仕掛ける[しかける]:to start|to challenge|to set (traps), 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
先に仕掛けた あんたが悪いのよ
You're the one who started it, so you've got it coming.
分裂[ぶんれつ]:split/division/break up
（フミエ）
おっ やるな！　分裂した
She's top-notch! She split in two.
Okay,
仕事にかかる[しごとにかかる]:to get to work, かしら:I wonder, かしら:head|hair (on one's head)
さあ こっちも
仕事にかかろうかしら
now we're going to make our move as well!
見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife)
見えた
Gotcha.
お… お前 何やった？
Wh-What's up with you?
メガネ:spectacles/glasses, 壊れる[こわれる]:to be broken/to break|to fall through
メガネが壊れました
My glasses... broke down.
空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, ハッキング:hacking
この空間がハッキングされている
This Space is being hacked!
Where's the hacking coming from?
一体[いったい]:...the heck (e.g. "what the heck?")|one object|one form||, ハッキング:hacking
一体 どこからハッキングしてる？
Access to the domain she's in is blocked!
ドメイン:domain, アクセス:access, 全て[すべて]:everything/all|entirely, はじく:to flip/to snap|to repel
あいつのいるドメインからの
アクセスは全て はじいてるぞ
The attack is coming from two different places!
攻撃[こうげき]:attack/strike|criticism, か所[かしょ]:passage/place/point
攻撃は２か所からです
Why that...!
おのれ:oneself (itself, etc.)|I/me, 違い[ちがい]:difference/discrepancy
おのれ！　１つはフミエに違いない
No doubt one of them is Fumie...
So they're working together.
結託[けったく]:conspiracy/collusion
ヤツら結託したんだ
I don't think so. Look over here!
くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
（アキラ）
違います 見てください！
They're in a completely different area.
全然[ぜんぜん]:not at all (with neg. verb)|wholly/entirely, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
（ガチャギリ）
全然違う場所にいるな
So which is the real one?
どっち:which way/which direction|which one (esp. of two alternatives), 本物[ほんもの]:genuine article/real thing/real deal
（ダイチ）
じゃあ どっちが本物だ？
None of them is the real one.
どっち:which way/which direction|which one (esp. of two alternatives), 本物[ほんもの]:genuine article/real thing/real deal
どっちも本物じゃない 本物は…
The real one is...
Here!
いたわ！
分裂[ぶんれつ]:split/division/break up
んなバカな！
あいつら分裂したのか？
How could she possibly...!
Did she split in two or what?
Can you figure out where her real location is?
現実[げんじつ]:reality/actuality/hard fact, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho, どっち:which way/which direction|which one (esp. of two alternatives)
現実の場所は
どっちか分かるか？
She's using a proxy to disguise herself.
偽装[ぎそう]:camouflage/disguise|pretense
偽装している
I can try,
やってみる:to have a go/to try and do (something)/to take a chance with something, かぎり:limit/limits|degree
やってみるが
ヤツがボロでも出さないかぎり
but if she doesn't reveal herself, I'm not sure I can find her.
見つかる[みつかる]:to be found/to be discovered
見つかるかどうか…
Namecchi.
ナメッチ！
Two years'
お年玉[おとしだま]:New Year's gift (usu. money given to a child by relatives and visitors)
お年玉 ２年分…
otoshidama...
Namekawa!
滑川(なめかわ)！
（ナメッチ）へい！
Yeah!
You don't have glasses anymore, so work out with your legs!
メガネ:spectacles/glasses, 足[あし]:foot|leg|gait||, 足[そく]:counter for pairs (of socks, shoes, etc.), 稼げる[かせげる]:to work/to earn income
お前 メガネないんだから足で稼げ
Go and take her glasses!
メガネ:spectacles/glasses, 取り上げる[とりあげる]:to pick up|to adopt|to take away|
ヤツのメガネを取り上げてこい！
R-Right!
へ… へい
So they modified
空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 設計[せっけい]:plan/design/layout, 改良[かいりょう]:improvement/reform
（イサコ）空間の設計ミスを
あいつが改良したのか
a structural error of the Space...
I see.
なるほど:I see/That's right!/Indeed, 方[かた]:direction|person|method of||, 方[ほう]:direction|side (of an argument, etc.)|type||, 覚える[おぼえる]:to memorize|to learn|to feel|, 面白い[おもしろい]:interesting|amusing|pleasant
なるほど
使い方を覚えると面白いわね
Learning how it works can be very useful.
Okay, boys.
よし お前たち いけ！
Go!
（モジョたち）モジョ！
Geez...
見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing
（フミエ）何よ
あいつ まだ見つけられないの？
Haven't they located her yet?
Hell,
まったく:really/truly|indeed, 世話が焼ける[せわがやける]:to be troublesome/to require the aid and labour of others
まったく… 世話が焼けるわね
they're useless!
場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho, 階[かい]:storey|stairs|stage (in chronostratigraphy)|, 階[しな]:article|quality|flirtatiousness, 元[もと]:origin|base|cause||, 元[げん]:unknown (e.g. in an equation)|element (of a set)|yuan (monetary unit of China)|, 理科[りか]:science, 室[しつ]:room|wife (of someone of high rank)|scabbard|
あれ？　場所が分かったぞ
１階の元理科室だ
I found her location!
She's inside the old lab on the first floor.
What?
なんだって？　なんで分かった？
And how did you find out?
Hmm... How did I get that?
なんで分かったんだろう…
Is there a shortcut linking there?
ショートカット:shortcut, つながる:to be tied together/to be connected to|to lead to
ショートカットはつながってるか？
Yes, there is.
あります
Alright!
ようし:(physical) appearance (of a person)/one's face and figure, ようし:blank form|sheets of paper/sheet of paper, とっておき:reserve/spare|treasured
ようし！　とっておきを出せ
Let's play our trump card!
Yeah!
へい
Huh? It's not here!
あれ？　な… ないよ
What?!
電話[でんわ]:telephone call/phone call|telephone (device)
（ダイチ）何？
クソ！　ナメッチに電話して…
Dammit!
Call Namecchi—
Ah, he hasn't got glasses!
メガネ:spectacles/glasses
あっ メガネないんだ あいつ…
直接[ちょくせつ]:direct/immediate/personal
直接 行くぞ！
Let's go there directly!
かます:barracuda, かます:to force something into someone's mouth (i.e. a gag)|to wedge something into a space, filling it
どてかましたれやー！
（ガチャギリ）おりゃー！
We'll blast her for good!
Yeah!
ああっ！　ま… 待って！
W-Wait!
（ナメッチ）イ… イサコちゃん？
Isako...
いますか～？
Are you in here?
For the teacher's personal use inside the lab.
使える[つかえる]:to be usable/to be serviceable/to be useful
ヘヘッ 使えるかな
I wonder if I can use 'em...
Recovering from Standby
Starting OS
イヤ～！
偽物[にせもの, にせもん]:spurious article/forgery/counterfeit
なんてことなの… これも偽物？
What's going on?
Another fake?
本体[ほんたい, ほんだい]:substance|main part|this machine||, コマンド:(computer) command, 逆探知[ぎゃくたんち]:phone trace/detecting the source of a telephone call
本体が出しているコマンドを
逆探知すれば…
If only we could trace back to the real one
that's giving the commands.
あと もうちょっと…
Just a little more...
見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing
見つけたわ！
Found her!
入れる[いれる]:to put in|to admit|to accept||
チェッ 入れない
I can't get in.
This is...
障壁[しょうへき]:enclosing wall/boundary fence|obstacle
これは… 障壁だわ
A firewall!
Number Five, don't eat it,
番[ばん]:number (in a series)|(one's) turn|watch|, 番[つがい]:(one) pair (e.g. of birds)/brace|joint, 食う[くう]:to eat|to live|to bite||
（イサコ）５番 食うな　死ぬぞ
or you'll die.
（モジョ）ジョ…
よーし:alright/all right/right on, 発射[はっしゃ]:firing/shooting|ejaculation, 準備[じゅんび]:preparation/setup/arrangements
よーし 発射準備！
Alright.
Prepare to move out!
Another hacker?
客[きゃく, かく]:guest/visitor|customer, 客[まろうど, まろうと]:visitor from afar/guest
別の客か
Just wait.
なさる:to do, 片づける[かたづける]:to tidy up|to settle (problem)|to finish||
待ってなさい
今 片づけるから
I'll take care of you, too.
If only I could find an unguarded spot...
隙[すき, げき]:gap|break|chink (in one's armor, armour)|, 見つかる[みつかる]:to be found/to be discovered
（フミエ）隙さえ見つかれば…
Here it is!
隙[すき, げき]:gap|break|chink (in one's armor, armour)|
隙ができた！
It went through!
通る[とおる]:to go by|to run (between)|to go indoors||
通った！
I hope she doesn't notice it.
気づく[きづく]:to notice/to recognize/to recognise
気づくなよ
The only weapons we have left are these firecrackers.
残り[のこり]:remnant/residue/remaining, 武器[ぶき]:weapon/arms|weapon (something used to gain an advantage)
残りの武器は
このカンシャクだけだ
Don't fail!
落とす[おとす]:to drop|to clean off (dirt, makeup, paint, etc.)|to lose (a match)||
落とすなよ
Charge!
突っ込む[つっこむ]:to thrust (something) into (something)|to plunge into|to get involved with|
（ダイチ）突っ込めー！
（ガチャギリ）やあー！
This toy is very interesting.
オモチャ:toy/plaything, 面白い[おもしろい]:interesting|amusing|pleasant, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
（イサコ）このオモチャ面白いな
もらっておくわ
I'll just keep it for myself.
You're finally here.
お待たせ
I'll let you play with me.
遊ぶ[あそぶ, あすぶ]:to play|to mess about (with alcohol, gambling, philandery, etc.)|to be idle||, 遊ぶ[すさぶ]:to grow wild/to rage|to do something one enjoys, あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair)
遊んであげる
D-Damn it!
こ… この！
Well done.
やるね
With all my power...!
実力[じつりょく]:(real) ability/true strength|arms
じ… 実力で
Fumie...
フミエちゃん？
I told you I would use all of my power to make you understand!
実力[じつりょく]:(real) ability/true strength|arms
じ… 実力で
分からせてやるんだから！
This old method
古流[こりゅう]:old manners/old style/old school (of art), 所詮[しょせん, そせん]:after all
古流じゃ 所詮(しょせん) ムリムリ
is useless!
Smash it!
潰れる[つぶれる]:to be crushed|to become useless|to go bankrupt
潰れろ！
Connection Interrupted
Fumie?
フ… フミエちゃん？
This means that Daichi
ショートカット:shortcut, 使える[つかえる]:to be usable/to be serviceable/to be useful
ショートカットを使えるのは
ダイチだけじゃないってことよ
Download is Complete
isn't the only one able to use shortcuts.
So she was even able to steal some information from me.
情報[じょうほう]:information/news|information, かすめ取る[かすめとる]:to snatch/to steal
私から情報をかすめ取るとはね
I understand your real power,
実力[じつりょく]:(real) ability/true strength|arms, 小さな[ちいさな]:small/little/tiny, 魔女[まじょ]:witch
実力は分かったわ 小さな魔女さん
little witch.
Four years'
お年玉[おとしだま]:New Year's gift (usu. money given to a child by relatives and visitors)
（ナメッチ）お年玉 ４年分…
otoshidama...
Ah, my back is so stiff!
肩[かた]:shoulder, 寿命[じゅみょう]:life span, 縮む[ちぢむ, ちじむ]:to shrink/to contract/to diminish (in size)
（フミエ）
あ～ 肩こった！　寿命 縮んだ
I've lost years of my life...
You were great, Fumie.
すごい:terrible/dreadful|amazing (e.g. of strength)
すごかったわ フミエちゃん
Well?
情報[じょうほう]:information/news|information, 見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife)
どうどう？　情報 見えた？
Can you see anything useful?
This is no good.
こりゃ:hey there/I say/see here, 乱暴[らんぼう]:rude/violent/rough, 引き抜く[ひきぬく]:to extract/to pull out|to headhunt, 壊れる[こわれる]:to be broken/to break|to fall through
（メガばあ）こりゃダメじゃな
乱暴に引き抜いたんで壊れとる
You grabbed it in the middle of a fight, so it got corrupted.
苦労[くろう]:troubles/hardships
え～　じゃあ
私の苦労はムダだったの？
So all my efforts were useless?
But we can read something in this piece.
辺[へん]:area|side|circumstances, 辺[へ, べ]:surrounding area|shore (of the sea)|suffix used as a rough indicator of location, direction, time, etc., 読む[よむ]:to read|to count|to guess
まあ でも この辺だけは
なんとか読めるな
Just that?!
取る[とる]:to take|to steal|to eat||
これだけ？
あ～ ムダに年取った
I lost years in vain.
Preview
Next time on Dennou Coil:
Metabug Scramble Bus Tour.
Metabug Scramble
Bus Tour
See you next time!
次回[じかい]:next time (occasion), 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, コイル:coil
（ヤサコ）
次回 「電脳コイル」
争奪[そうだつ]:struggle/contest, バスツアー:bus tour
〝メタバグ争奪
バスツアー 〞
楽しみ[たのしみ]:enjoyment/pleasure|anticipation
お楽しみに